hi I'm go from JH nether and in this
video I'm going to show you how to hand
stitch leather let's get started
[Music]
so quick comparison with machine
stitching versus hand stitching so with
machine stitching that's two lengths of
thread and basically lays of twists in
the middle of the leather to create the
stitch so you'll notice on your clothes
if you have a little loose thread and
you pull at it you can have a whole lot
of length of stitching becomes
unstitched that is because it is made up
of two lengths of thread so with hand
stitching where it's one length of
thread basically each stitch is an
individual stitch so if one comes sort
of long breaks it's not going to unravel
because each stitch is individual which
is why hand stitching for leather work
is just great because you know if you're
on a dog collar and that it gets a lot
of wear it's you know it's not going to
come and stitched right so onto our hand
stitching so this exercise is one that I
do with students and basically we're
gonna take a scrap bit of leather and
square the ends and we're also going to
Nick the corners
I sort of squared your ends you then
want to number one edge all the way
around the grain side of your leather
and then once you done that we can now
stain the edges and polish them and
switch it on staining you can crease all
the way around your leather so you
basically need to crease it up and then
just draw a line around your sample and
worse than that you want to set your
dividers to your stitch marking with
mine are usually around a quarter of an
inch and then you can draw all the way
around your sample so onto stitching so
I use a number 7 pricking iron so that
seven stitches per inch is what I use
for most of my dog collars and bounce
and that sort of thing
I can also use the diamond chisels which
I made to go all the way through it is
just up to you what you have and what is
you use
so once you're done stitch marking you
want to cut yourself a length of thread
so I usually do about a double arm's
length and then with some B so actually
just want to run the thread through this
so this adds a layer of protection to
the thread especially if it is linen and
it also smooths down any sort of loose
fibers so I should run your thread
through the wax a few times you can then
just run it for your fingers to really
work the beeswax into your thread and
now we want to start threading so we're
going to lock our thread onto the needle
so first of all you want to put just
about an inch or so off that thread
through the eye of the needle and they
were actually going to put the needle
through the thread itself so we can lock
it on so we're going to do this twice so
we're gonna have like a little S shape
like what I have here and then basically
we need to move all that down the needle
and then sort of over the end of the eye
and that will lock our thread on to our
needle so it won't fall off and we're
going to do the same on the other end so
we're gonna put the thread from the eye
of the needle about an inch or so over
the way through and then the sort of
long end of the thread we're going to
put the needle through that twice make a
little S shape and then pull the whole
lot down over the eye of needle so it's
all locked on there so onto the
stitching so we're going to start with a
back stitch which once you've seen this
video a few times and you understand the
technique it will make a bit more sense
so basically we do a back stitch to lock
the thread in place especially for you
going onto doing buccal turns and stuff
like that you need to do a back stitch
to get the ends of your leather together
right so like I said you may need to
watch some video a few times to get the
technique but basically what we want to
do is all through our whole from the
right hand side first
and then we gonna follow that through
with the needle from the left
I wish your left her need a list of
partway through you want to basically
make a little cross with your right hand
needle underneath and pull that out and
then you can sort of turn with your
hands and put that right hand needle
that made up the tears across back three
and then you want to pop the tail of
your thread over that needle and then
you can pull tight and pull your needle
through so that is the basic technique
because like I said you might need to
watch this a few times just to get the
technique right it is a bit confusing to
start with and if you find it hard
stitching with an awl in your hands you
can maybe all a few or if you've got
your diamond picking irons and you've
all order all the way through you might
not even need an awl at all
so just to recap we all through from the
right follow through the left with a
needle make a cross with our right hand
needle but I write our needle through
and then put the tail end of the thread
over the needle so by doing that it
makes sure that the stitches all sort of
slant the same way
and so if you need to change your thread
because you've run out and you're
stitching a long distance or you just
come to finish your actual stitching you
need to do one and a half back stitches
and so what this is is literally we're
going to go one whole stitch back and
then with our right hand needle we're
going to go back through just with that
one so for the half and what this does
it just locks the stitches in place and
also make sure that both threads are on
the backside of what we are stitching
and so once you've done that you can
then trim the threads off and if you're
going to start a new bit of stitching
you would start with one back stitch and
carry on or if that was the end of your
stitching then you would go on to do
your finishing touches so that's it for
this video thank you very much for
watching if you liked the video please
click thumbs up button and subscribe for
more videos and tutorials also make sure
you hit the bell button to get notified
every time I post a new video and I'll
see you in the next episode